Shit!
该死
Did I hurt myself?
受伤了
My God - blood!
出血了
- Everything okay, Marcel? - No.
你还好吗
What do you think, with the middle of my face smashed in?
我的脸刚才受伤了
Red wine.
要红酒
These glasses are smaller than a drunkard's dreams.
这不是干净的杯子
- Any luck with the publisher? - No, the swine!
出版社怎么样 说我的戏曲太长了
He said it was too long and demanded cuts,
也不给我定金  只是叫我写短一点
but with no promises and no advance - the lout!
混蛋
- Why not let me read it? - You?
能给我看看吗 你
Yes, me.
是的
You can read?
你识字吗
Are you kidding?
可以看懂
I finished third grade in Mongéo before coming to Paris.
我在小学的时候已经学过
I'll read it at bedtime.
我想在入睡之前念
Why not?
好吧我借给你
You'll give me the people's appraisal
看完后告诉我你的感想
and put the publishers to shame.
希望你能看出出版商  没能看出的东西
The Avenger - A Play in 21 Acts by Marcel Marx
"复仇者"21幕剧
EVICTION NOTICE
马上搬出去
Good morning, Monsieur Marcel. Have you forgotten that today is the eighth?
马歇尔先生  我们已经说好8日退房吧
Already? How time rushes on!
这么快就到时间了吗
You're a bit slow in vacating the premises.
请搬出去
It's already 11:30.
已经11点半了  下一位住户到了
The new tenant may arrive at any moment. Allow me to find a moving van.
请帮我叫一下出租车
By all means!
谢谢
But there's one little formality to see to first:
但之前还有点事情要做
your three months' back rent. Would you mind? - Of course not.
你还没有交3个月的房租
Then kindly step into my office, so I may give you a receipt.
我会付清的 如果你到事务所  我会给你开单
- When I return. - Why not now?
回来之后马上过去 现在马上
I must go to the bank. I don't carry a sum like that on me.
不去银行就没有钱给你
I see. No cash.
那就没办法了
Then allow me to relieve you of that little burden
等你回来之前  我会替你保管这些东西
so it doesn't tire you. You think I'd carry off my belongings in a bag?
如果这里面  有贵重东西怎么办
Those are the rules.
这是规矩
You're not to remove so much as a single hair until the rent is paid.
付清房租之前  你别想拿走任何东西
There's no hair in here,
里面是我的衬衫
just shirts I'm taking to the laundry next door to the bank, just steps from here.
我想拿到银行隔壁的洗衣房
Please do not misunderstand me,
你把我当成傻瓜吗
but certain unfortunate experiences
租房子的人不可信  这是我长年的经验
have shattered my faith in tenants.
Hugo had best accompany you to the bank.
尤高会跟你一起去银行
摩勒克福银行
See this man? He's been casing this bank for three days.
这家伙一直  在银行周围转来转去
I live across the street. His accomplice is around the corner in an Alfa Romeo,
还有一个就在那里  他一直装作看报纸
reading Le Monde - upside down.
在车上看哨
I only wish to do my duty.
因为我的所有财产都在
My life's savings are in this bank.
这个银行所以我向你告发
What do you suppose is in his bag?
请搜查他的包
Has my apartment been vacated?
房子已经空出来了吧
Not yet, Monsieur Schaunard, but very soon.
我马上收拾好
The previous tenant, a writer, has gone to get a moving van.
之前住过的人把箱子  放在我这里就走了
In the meantime, you may leave your furniture outside.
我帮你搬东西到走廊
I'm afraid. If it rains, my furniture will be damaged.
如果下雨家具会潮湿
You will forgive me if I ask your profession.
你是做什么工作的
You neglected to indicate that on the lease.
在合同上没有
Leave the piano here and return at once to my old lodgings
钢琴就这么放着 到公寓  把高档家私搬过来吧
for the rest of my priceless furnishings and works of art.
还有我的艺术品
Henri, from the Ministry of War. It just arrived by courier.
是国防大臣的信 刚刚到
The Ministry of War.
国防大臣
It must be the pension
是我期待已久的  养老金领取书
that I've been waiting for all these years. At last some recognition of my achievements.
终于可以拿到钱了
Dear Monsieur Bernard, courtesy demands that I inform you
"贝尔那先生" "我把我的不幸遭遇告诉你"
of the unfortunate predicament I find myself in that prevents me at this time from observing the custom
"这次之后"
requiring that rent be paid, especially when it's due.
"不会再付房租了"
Until this morning I had hoped
"到今天早上为止  我都想付清房租"
to honor this lo very day by paying my rent - ah, delusion!
As I slept cradled in false certainty, misfortune -
"但和我的期待相反"
Ananke in Greek - dashed my hopes.
"我的这些想法被打破了"
Certain sizable sums I expected did not materialize,
"我没有钱"
but our beautiful France and I will see better days - have no doubt of that.
"我相信幸运之神  会降临在法国和我身上"
The moment we do, I shall hasten to inform you of it
"有了收入之后我会马上通知你"
and to remove from my lodgings my precious possessions,
"再取回留在房子里的  我的贵重品"
which I leave to your safekeeping and to that of the law,
那之前先让您  和法律来保护它吧
which restrains you from selling them for one year.
"不要在一年之内  处理那些东西"
Until then you are at liberty to use
"那之前请随便使用房间"
the luxurious lodgings in which I have resided. In affirmation of my consent, I hereby affix my signature.
"我在这里把这件事告诉您"
Marcel Marx.
"马歇尔·马科斯"
- Two half orders of trout. - Yes, sir.
给我半份鳟鱼
That's a strange order.
奇怪的要求
On the contrary. This method yields on average
那是经过计算之后得出来的
a quarter more than ordering a full portion.
这比要一份量更多
Where is my order?
我的呢
I'm afraid this gentleman got the last trout.
鳟鱼料理已经不做了
May I invite you to partake of this course with me?
不介意和我分吧
I would not deprive you of what is yours, sir.
我不想夺取你的食物
Then you'd deprive me of the pleasure of expressing my goodwill?
你想无视我的好意吗
In that case, sir...
那我就不客气了
Permit me to refrain from serving you the head.
鱼头我吃
That I couldn't allow.
这对你不公平
For if the head is man's noblest appendage,
人类的大脑中  需要一些养分
it's the most unpleasant part of a trout.
鳟鱼的头可以满足这些需要
Two heads! This trout is bicephalic,
有两个头双头  原本是希腊语
a word which comes from the Greek and means... precisely that.
怎么会有双头的鳟鱼
Nevertheless, I harbor no regrets about eating this phenomenon.
吃一些奇形怪状的鱼  已经很普遍
The sauce was delicious.
真是好吃的料理
True. It was prepared in the province of Béarn,
我也这么认为
and its fine reputation is richly deserved.
这里都是些有名的料理
You seem very learned. You're not from here?
你怎么会对这里这么熟悉  是巴黎人吗
No. I come from Albania
我是阿尔巴尼亚人
and have lived in Paris only three years now.
住在巴黎已经有3年了
Yet you've already mastered our language.
讲法语真棒
My nursemaid was French, from Barcelona.
我的乳娘是从巴塞罗那  来的法国人
My name is Rodolfo, and I'm a painter.
我叫罗德洛夫是画家
Marcel Marx, writer.
我是作家马科斯
May I offer you a bottle of wine?
我想请你喝酒
Only on one condition:
我有条件
that I see to the coffee and the rest.
咖啡由我自己拿
As a painter, don't you think
作为画家你有什么意见
that Malevich's Black Square
就像马雷奇  改变绘画的方向一样
is as lethal a blow to painting as the school of Vienna - Schoenberg, Berg, Webern, and the rest - is to music?
肖恩等流派的人
- I agree entirely. - Let's go.
改变了音乐 要走了
I live just around the corner. We may continue our discussion there.
我住在附近  到我那里继续说吧
“I floated down impassive rivers, unguided now by bargemen's hands.
"我喝醉了  坐在船上在河上行驶"
Howling natives had hauled them up for targets
"不幸的是  船被印第安人打沉了"
and nailed them naked to painted stakes.” Beautiful stuff, Rimbaud.
是兰博
He and Verlaine argued vehemently about -
Anyway, come inside.
This is where I live.
这里就是我家
谢谢
Strange. The key's in the lock, though I put it in my pocket this morning -
糟了  我把钥匙放在房间窗户上
where it remains even now.
你先在这里等着
It's witchcraft! Two keys.
你变魔法了  有两个钥匙
Someone's playing the violin. These aren't my lodgings.
是钢琴声音真奇怪
May I help you?
有什么事吗
I was mistaken. This isn't my apartment.
我还以为这是我的房子
I beg your pardon on my friend's behalf.
失礼了他喝醉了
He's exceptionally drunk. Wait, this is my place.
我还以为是我的房子...
That's my finery!
那是我的衣服
And what's this?
这是什么
My Turkish slippers, given to me by beloved hands!
这是朋友送给我的拖鞋
“Marcel Marx is hereby obligated to vacate the premises
"马歇尔·马科斯先生  到8日正午之前"
by noon on February eighth...”
"请马上退房"
Am I not the Marcel Marx
我就是被他赶走的  马歇尔·马科斯
whom the landlord evicted?
我听说过
The situation is as follows. By law
法律上这里是我的房间
the premises are mine, for you were evicted, and I paid in advance.
你被房东赶走  我就搬进来住了
Yes, for the premises, but not the furnishings.
房子是你的没错  但这些家具就不是
If I pay up, I may remove them legally -
即使没有交房租  家具也是我的
or even illegally, if it were possible. Thus you have furnishings but no lodgings,
你可以拿回家具  但没有房子
and I have lodgings but no furniture. - Precisely.
我不会让你住进来
I like the apartment.
这里真是不错的房子
And I've never liked it more. - Pardon?
是很脏的房子
Never as much as now, and I know what I'm saying.
但给你住就有点可惜了
What do you say we lubricate this explanation?
慢点说吧
What an amazing pipe you have.
真是不错的茬子
I have an even more handsome one for use in high society.
我在上流社会的时候  拿着都是名贵的东西
Would you care to try it? - With pleasure.
你试一下 谢谢
You appear to be a man of musical bent.
你是音乐迷吗
A composer.
我是作曲家
I'm writing a piece called
现在正准备新的曲子
“The Influence of Blue on the Arts.”
是叫做  "蓝色对艺术的影响"的作品
- I can't see anyone just now. - Why not?
现在不行 为什么
Good morning.
中午好
Good morning, mademoiselle.
马托摩洁丽
- There's my answer. - I understand.
这就是原因 知道了
All the same, perhaps you might lend me 1,000 francs.
借我100法郎
I'm all out of paint,
涂料用完了
and I can't complete my masterpiece.
我完成不了  正在创作中的画
You're asking a lot. I'm broke at the moment.
我也是个穷光蛋
Couldn't you borrow it from the girl?
你跟那个女人说说看
I couldn't do that. We just met yesterday.
不行她是昨天才认识的
- And Schaunard? - No one's seen him all week.
肖纳罗呢 这一周一直没见到他  回去吧
Good-bye.
Where are you going?
你去哪里
To your place... to collect what you owe me.
我想要回借给你的钱
You won't find me at home.
真遗憾
I can't pay you back today. I'm waiting for a girl.
今天有约会所以不能还给你
But you can pawn my ring.
你先拿着这个戒指
There she is.
来了
Beat it.
快点消失
What if she comes back to you?
如果卖掉戒指  你妻子会难过的
You'd no longer have the ring.
She won't come back.
她不会再回来了
She ran off with an American.
她和开卡迪拉克的  美国人跑掉了
He had a Cadillac. It's a shame about the children.
留下孩子们
She left them with me,
因为没有钱  我无法买东西给孩子们吃
and I don't have enough to feed them.
They cry out from hunger in the night.
晚上因为肚饿哭个不停
How old are they?
孩子几岁了
Fourteen... nine...
14岁小的9岁
seven... six... three... two...
还有7岁的6岁的  3岁的和1岁的
one... and the youngest is just six months.
最小的只有6个月
So many!
真是人山人海啊
We were young and in love.
是冲动造成的
It was spring.
现在还年轻
You look strange.
怎么样
What's the matter?
什么
I think I have fallen in love.
我想谈恋爱
With whom?
有目标吗
I don't know... but she's sitting over there.
是不知名的女人  正坐在对面
She's not bad-looking.
不错的女人
Why don't you do something?
诱惑看看
What if she rejects me?
如果被拒绝
I'd never get over it.
我就没面子了
It's our custom in Albania to first -
在我故乡阿尔巴尼亚
You stay here.
看我的
I'll go speak to her on your behalf.
我帮你试试看
I will awaken in her heart a passion...
在她的心中点燃一股火焰
for you. I will lie
用甜言蜜语
shamelessly.
Good evening.
你好
See that man over there? He is in love with you.
坐在对面的男人看上了你
But so am I.
我也是
Excuse me. Can I help you?
怎么了
I fell asleep.
已经睡着了
Where are you going?
你是访客
Nowhere.
我是从乡下过来的
I arrived in town, but my girlfriend isn't in.
来探望朋友但她不在
I was to stay with her. It's no use waiting.
等了也没用还有3年的牢要坐
She was taken to prison, for three years.
What am I going to do now?
真为难
I arrived today from Rouen. I don't know anyone here.
我在巴黎没有认识人
If you like... I live next door.
我是她的邻居你进来休息吧
Tell me: Are you a proper French gentleman?
你是绅士一样的法国人吧
No.
是没错
I mean, yes... but I'm not French. I'm Albanian.
我是阿尔巴尼亚人
That Will do.
好吧
I'm going now and taking the dog with me.
我带狗出去
He sometimes makes noise at night due to nightmares.
你睡觉的时候狗会吠个不停
But why? I can sleep on the sofa.
为什么出去  我在沙发睡就可以了
It's too hard for a bed.
在沙发睡觉不会舒服
And besides... I'm hot-blooded, and you are very beautiful.
而且我动作很快你又这么漂亮
- Where will you go? - To a friend's.
那你去哪里 就在附近的朋友家
He lives close by.
Sleep peacefully. I'll be back in the morning.
慢慢睡吧  明天早上我才回来
Baudelaire.
波特里
"安里·穆杰鲁"
“I have gone to seek lodgings. Thank you for your kindness. Mimi.” Where's your black coat?
"我正在找住的地方  谢谢你的款待眯米" 黑色上衣呢
Can't you see?
就这个
You've ruined it.
已经弄脏了
I'm lost.
I've been summoned by Gassot, the newspaper czar.
我和新闻王见面
He's founding a fashion magazine, The Sash of Iris,
我面试一个新增杂志的编辑
and plans to make me editor in chief. If I show up in this getup, he may change his mind.
就这样去的话肯定不行
You can't accept his offer anyway.
那种事情还是早点别想
Gassot is a supporter of the right.
卡索是右翼分子
Your principles won't allow you to eat bread
你想帮榨取民脂民膏的  人做事吗
bathed in the sweat of the people. - You're mistaken. He's in the left flank of the right wing in Parliament.
不他在右翼中也倾向左派
Just yesterday he voted for widows' pensions.
他提倡遗孤补偿金  而且还认识很多大人物
Besides, he knows influential people whom I'll convince to commission
这是你们两个出名的好机会
compositions from you and portraits from Rodolfo. That changes everything. What time's your meeting?
那还可以  你什么时候和他见面
At 5100.
5点
There's no time to lose.
那就快点吧
I can polish my shoes black
把鞋子涂成黑色
so no one will notice
那样的话  就算两边不一样也不易发现
that one is round-toed and the other pointed.
I need a black coat!
我需要件黑色上衣
I'd give ten years of my life and my right hand for one.
如果不想点办法
- Is Rodolfo the painter in? - That's me.
洛特勒夫在吗 就是我
My cousin recommends your reasonably priced portraits.
你的肖像画好像很受欢迎
I'm told they're very good likenesses. More accurate than photographs.
比书上的更好
He's very talented.
学校还让他过去教学生
He won every award at school. My son won an award, and he's only seven.
我儿子已经7岁  在学校也拿过奖
A talented child.
真是神童
This portrait you want, Monsieur...
你要那幅画
Blancheron, from Nantes. I'm a sugar producer.
我是砂糖工厂老板佛兰修罗
I've even written books on the subject.
而且写过关于砂糖的著作
I'd like a medium-sized portrait.
我要一个很大的画
Like that one. Who is that of?
是谁的肖像呢
My mother.
是我母亲
How much would one of that size cost?
那么大的多少钱
Between 1,000 and 1,200 francs,
1000到1200法郎
depending on whether your hands show.
这个价钱很合理
- My cousin said 500. - It depends on the season.
500怎么样
Paint prices vary with the season.
因为画具的价钱也会改变
- Interesting. Just like sugar. - Precisely.
和砂糖市场一样吗 没错
- Paint me one for 1,000 francs. - You're making a mistake.
那就1000法郎
For 200 more, he'll paint your hands holding your book on sugar.
如果再给多200法郎 可以把你的书加到画里面
You simply must do it. - Would that look good?
就这样定了
Exceptionally good.
就在你家里画吗
Is the portrait for your home?
在我的寝室画
Yes, the living room. Then you must be in a dressing gown.
那就穿便装最好了
Please sit in this chair.
请坐
Take off your coat.
换衣服
I don't have a dressing gown with me.
我没有便装
Don't worry. My friend will lend you his.
不用担心穿着这个就可以
Marcel, please hang up the gentleman's coat.
马歇尔把上衣挂好
How unfortunate. I'll be late for supper.
我现在有点饿了
The restaurant downstairs will send up anything we want.
下面的餐厅可以送餐过来
I'll go order something.
我可以帮你叫
I have several ideas to improve the contents of your magazine.
那是杂志"彩虹"的创刊号
For instance, one could - this is just one possibility -
我对此有很好的计划
one could publish a play,
我们可以连载戏曲
and on the facing pages show the characters
豪华的登场人物
dressed in a certain way as if it were the fashion -
穿着最新流行的服装  在那里演绎故事
the latest fashion, of course. One could also envision
我还有一个  正在准备中的计划
other things, like, for example, publishing the works of Baudelaire
把波特里的生涯  写成连载怎么样
in serial form -
When may I come for it?
什么时候完成
I'll finish it tomorrow and bring it to you.
明天早上我会送到府上
I'd prefer to pay at once so as not to remain in debt to you.
我想拿到画之后再给你钱
We're alike in that respect.
可以
My cash is at the hotel. You'll have it tomorrow.
明天在酒店给你钱
Now, if you'd get me my coat...
那我的上衣呢
It was very dusty, so I had it laundered.
我已经洗干净了
They only charged 40 francs.
洗衣服花了40法郎
Just add it to my bill.
寄给我发票
I'm not paying a thing!
不用给了
Shit!
笨蛋
The swine!
蠢猪
He wanted to charge me
才走了几公里就叫我给钱
for a few miles.
There must be 60,000 francs there.
这里该有6万法郎吧
15,240, to be precise -
正确的数字是1万5240法郎
an advance for producing a sample issue of The Sash of Iris.
这是做  "彩虹"创刊编辑的订金
Here's my plan.
我决定了
Secure from life's material woes,
为了脱离贫困  我要拼命做事
I intend to go about this seriously. First I'll get rid of these rags and dress decently
首先要买一套漂亮的衣服
so that the fashion salons will take me seriously.
不能让他们小看我
If you'll follow my example,
你们也这么做吧  做点关于广告的事情
I can hire you as door-to-door ad salesmen.
他们马上会给你生活费
Until then, let a strict economy govern our lives.
I accept wholeheartedly.
大家好好合作
But to start with, give me a couple of thousand francs.
先给我2000～3000法郎
Why?
为什么
As a door-to-door salesman, I must have a car
要做广告就需要一辆车
to call on potential advertisers in the provinces.
有时候也要到乡下  弄一些广告题材
That's true.
没错
Shall we order a table?
吃饭吧
Yes. Then I can tell you more about my new job.
那边吃边说吧
There's an excellent restaurant not far from here.
这附近有一个高级餐厅
It's a bit expensive,
价格合理东西也好吃
but we'll make it up in the time we save.
Very well, but starting tomorrow
只有今天晚上  明天开始要节约生活
we shall devise even greater means of economizing. No more eating out. We'll hire a woman to cook for us.
取消在外面就餐  一切都在家里吃
It would be wiser to take on a manservant who could then double as cook.
雇一个庸人  来给我们做饭就好了
Our household would be in impeccable order
房子会变得很漂亮  而且也不贵
and we'd have much more time to work
我们也可以专心做事
with him to shine our shoes and see to our errands.
庸人会替你们擦好鞋子
Then we'll need larger accommodations.
若那样就需要一个很大的房子
That, in any case, is unavoidable
没错需要一个大点的楼房
if we mean to live in keeping with our new position in society.
不能给我们的名声抹黑
I'll be back.
我马上到
A pack of Celtiques, please.
给我一箱酒
Good evening, Mimi. You found work.
眯米找到事做了
As you can see.
没错
- And a place to live? - It comes with the job.
房子也找到了吗 有职工宿舍你们去酒吧吗
Are you going to the nightclub? I just came along with my friends.
没有只是碰巧到这里而已
I don't care for modern music.
虽然会喝酒  但我不喜欢嘈杂的音乐
I'm going to have a drink.
A glass of water, please.
给我杯水吧
- Who was that? - A regular.
那个男人是 他是我们这里的常客
He has the manners of a peasant.
看起来不怎么好
It's kind of you to see me home,
你送我回去我很高兴  但我住的地方很远
but this is nowhere near where I live.
I wish you lived in Moscow
就算是莫斯科也没问题
so I might have your company that much longer.
我想和你走到北的尽头
That's a bit too far.
会很远的
We could take the boulevard.
总会有到的时候
Fancy that.
真难以置信
We've arrived by chance where I live.
不知不觉到了我家了
Wouldn't you like to come up and say hello to the dog?
你不想见到我的狗吗
Very well, but just for a moment.
有一点
I'll make some coffee.
我去趟咖啡厅
In the meanwhile, you may enjoy the city view from my window.
期间从窗户欣赏街头景象吧
They wilted.
已经枯萎了
Had I known, I'd have bought
早知道买塑料花就好了
plastic flowers.
What's his name?
你的狗叫什么
Baudelaire.
波特里
I'm out of coffee,
你先喝咖啡我给你做汤
but I'll make some soup.
May I kiss your hand?
我可以吻你的手吗
You move fast.
你真性急
The sooner to reach the goal.
你管善良的人这么说吗
How much is this?
多少
A hundred francs.
100法郎
Fifty.
All right. For you, 50.
拿走吧
How about this?
不要领带吗
I live with two other girls.
和另外两个女人一起住
They have a male friend in common whom they're constantly fighting over.
她们两个为了一个男人  整天在吵架
I don't get it.
我不觉得怎么样
The man is stupid and ugly, and married to boot.
那个男人又蠢又丑陋  而且已经结婚了
Uglier than me?
比我还丑陋吗
There's no comparison. Next to him, you're Lino Ventura.
你跟他比起来  简直是个美男子
Who's that?
是吗
An Italian movie star. You don't know him?
你像意大利的名演员
Forget him.
忘了意大利的演员  我有话和你说
Let's talk about me. Why not... move in with me?
不想和我一起生活吗
I'm against marriage in principle,
虽然我是单身主义者
but we could make an exception.
但我喜欢和你在一起
You'll stop working. I'll support us both with my paintings.
不要做事了  我卖画就可以维持生活
And what would I do?
那我做什么
You'd walk Baudelaire, clean the place -
带狗散步 还有打扫房间和其它家务
that sort of thing.
做饭吗
Are you serious?
不用
I'll clean...
我会做
and you can look out the window at the park.
你只要  从窗户看着公园就可以了
In the evenings we'll go to the opera.
晚上可以到剧院看戏
My wallet's been stolen.
我的钱包被偷了  你带钱了吗
Do you have any money? Just a few francs.
我只有几法郎而已
Police?
是警察局吗
Your passport.
请出示身份证
Listen, how much is their check?
是多少钱
Four hundred twenty.
是420法郎
Will you allow me to pay it?
让我来吧
You think you'll get your money back from that burn?
他不会还你钱的
It doesn't matter.
没关系
Then as far as we're concerned, the matter is settled.
谢谢
I have to go now.
不走了
I start work at 9:00.
9点开始我要做事
I have to wait for my passport.
我等他们还给我护照
I'll come by your place tomorrow evening.
明晚见
I'll be waiting.
等等
Come with me.
过来
Why?
为什么
There's something suspicious about your papers.
有些不明的地方
You've resided in France for three years with no visa,
没有护照却在法国  不法居留三年
no residence permit, no work permit.
也没有劳动许可证
You claim you came by train from Spain,
你说自己是从西班牙  坐汽车来的
but you choose to say nothing more.
There is nothing more to say.
我没有那么说过
Very well.
是吗
You'll spend the night here.
关到拘留所
We'll decide your fate in the morning.
明天早上再决定怎么处理
May I make a call?
我想打电话家里只有狗
My dog is home alone. - In the morning.
明天
You're to be deported immediately to Albania.
坐两个小时候的航班  回阿尔巴尼亚
The flight for Athens leaves in two hours. If you're found within France's borders again
若以后还到法国非法居留
without the necessary papers, it will mean six months in jail.
就会让你坐6个月的牢
May I make a call now?
我现在可以打电话了吗
Make it fast.
要快点
Mimi hasn't arrived yet.
眯米还没来
I don't know.
没错
Try again in a couple of hours.
过一会再打过来吧
Morning, Henri.
刚有过你的电话
- Someone just called for you. - Who?
是谁
He didn't say.
不知道
Could you make me a coffee?
给我咖啡
马歇尔
Listen... I'm being deported.
我被他们遣送回国了
Will you look after Baudelaire and my paintings?
请收好波特里和我的画
I won't be coming back.
我不会再回来
They'll put me in jail if I do.
若以后再到法国就会蹲监狱
Understand?
Good-bye, Rodolfo.
保重
- A Suze. - Problems?
里库尔 什么
No. Just thirsty.
酒
What do you think?
怎么样  我只花了1800法郎
1,800 francs. Only 19,000 miles. It has brakes...
可以行驶2万公里  还有刹车也很好
and everything. Great. Are you free this evening?
真不错今天晚上有空吗
What's bothering you? You don't seem too enthusiastic.
你的脸色很难看怎么了
Rodolfds been deported. No papers.
洛特勒夫要回国了
Shit.
该死
I'll go get Baudelaire.
我带走狗还有他的画要搬出来
Let's meet there tonight and haul his paintings to your place.
All right.
知道了
Evening, ma'am.
晚上好
- Are you looking for Rodolfo? - Yes.
你找谁
We were to meet here. Where is he?
是的我们约好见面  他在哪里
He's been deported. He was in the country illegally.
因为非法居留  所以被遣送回国了
When?
什么时候
This afternoon.
今天下午
Is he coming back?
还回来吗
I don't know.
不知道
I have to go. Shut the door when you leave.
好了走吧  出来的时候把窗户关好
SPRING
春天
Hello, Musette. How's it going?
穆杰多你还好吗
What's it look like?
老样子
How many today? We have to go to press Friday.
广告有了吗  周五之前要印刷好
Just one, but a full page. For Printemps.
找到了一件  是"佛朗坦"的一面广告
I know. They called and cancelled it.
那个广告就取消吧
Coffee originated in Arabia, where it was discovered by a goat.
阿拉伯原产咖啡  是被亚奇发现的
Balzac drank 70 cups a day.
巴尔扎克一天会喝70多杯
What are you up to with that ladder?
那个梯子是什么
It's the link between me and my beloved.
这是连接我和我爱人的桥梁
Have you read Shakespeare? Of course. He was a great philosopher.
知道了你这个大哲学家
Do you remember Romeo and Juliet?
"罗米欧和朱丽叶"怎么样
Do I remember it?
歇尔夫...
“It was the nightingale and not the lark
"弄醒你的不是画眉鸟"
that pierced the fearful hollow of thine ear.”
"是耐辛盖尔"
Don't you understand?
就那样
I've met a girl from a good family,
我认识了一个大家闺秀
but for certain reasons her father can't stand me
她的父亲憎恨我  甚至想杀了我
and has threatened to kill me. The girl's name is Juliette,
她叫朱丽叶家里还有舞台
and her room just happens to have a balcony.
I came to borrow this bird
改天晚上借我这只小鸟
to wake me every morning before the old man gets up.
是为了第二天早上  比她父亲早起
I'd be obliged if from now on you'd call me
今天开始 叫我做罗米欧
Romeo Montague. What do you think of my plan?
太罗嗦了吧
The Sash of Iris, hello.
这里是"彩虹"编辑部
It's for you, Marcel, from abroad.
是一个外国人
All right.
你好
Where?
哪里
What time?
几点
Very well.
知道了
Forget about your Juliette. We have to go.
忘了你的恋人吧走
- Where? - The border.
去哪里
I'll explain on the way.
是边境后面再跟你解释
Let me have a few hundred. - There is no money.
先借我 没有
Where did it all go?
我看你有
I paid the printer so they'd give me the magazines.
印刷的时候用完了
You could have left them there.
那也会有一点
We need a picture for the cover.
我还要照相呢
Hold still.
别动
Now let's go.
There he is.
是他
Shall we go? We can make Paris by morning.
我想马上跑到巴黎
- When is Mimi in? - Mimi isn't here anymore.
眯米在吗 她已经不干了  但每天晚上都会过来玩
But they stop in almost every evening.
Who's “they”?
和什么人一起
Mimi and Francis, her boyfriend. Why do you ask?
和她的情人佛朗希斯一起  有什么事吗
I'm an old friend. Thank you.
她是我的老朋友
Good evening.
晚上好
How are you? - Fine.
还好吗
Someone was asking for you. - Who?
是啊你的朋友来了 谁
An old friend. He's sitting over there.
是你的老朋友在那边
I believe The Crossing of the Red Sea
眯米 "红海横断"  这幅画已经完成了
is finished. I feel empty.
但我不会卖
If you manage to sell it, we can pay the rent.
现在卖了才会有钱交租
Perhaps you could come down on the price.
便宜点卖吧
I won't sell it for less
200法郎以下我不会卖的
than 200 francs. I've already put
为了画这幅画  我花了1万法郎以上
over 10,000 francs' worth of paint into it. What if the landlord calls the police?
我担心你会被警察抓走
You still don't have a residence permit.
Come in.
请进
What a surprise.
真令人吃惊
眯米
Would you offer our guest a glass of water?
给客人倒一杯水吧
To what do I owe this honor?
有事吗
I was so inspired by your portrait
我喜欢上油画  现在变成了收藏家
that I've decided to become a collector. I'm now looking for a relatively large painting,
我想现在就要一幅大画
and I thought of you. You're in luck.
这幅画刚画好
I just finished this one and intended to send it off
和其它的作品一起
in the morning with some other works
明天早上要送走
to an exhibition in New York.
在纽约开展览会
But if you'd care to make an offer...
但也可以出售
as an old customer...
你是不错的买主
I like the work very much.
是个不错的作品
I'll give you 1,000 francs.
1000法郎怎么样
- You're joking. - 1,200.
太便宜了 1200法郎
2,000.
2000法郎
1,400.
1400法郎
1,700.
1700法郎
1,500...
1500法郎
and two tickets to the opera this evening.
再给你两张演出入场券
Opera is a dying art form, but all right.
虽然那些都是腐烂的艺术  但也好
Go pay the rent and then get dressed.
交了房租之后要买点衣服
You and Musette can go to the opera.
我们到剧院看戏
I'll wait outside.
我到外面和马歇尔见面
I have to talk to Marcel.
Poor girls.
强迫女人过贫穷的生活  太残酷了
They were never meant to live like this.
Being men, and thus stronger in every respect,
但男人很强大
we bear up joyfully under every misfortune.
就算遭受挫折也不会气馁
We don't sink into depression
每天穿着睡衣也可以生活
if our outfit isn't always neat and tidy.
But for women it's different.
但女人这样可不行
The simplest frock brings them joy, and one can't fault them for that.
为一件衣服欢欣鼓舞的就是女人
On the other hand,
最近美术或者  文化市场开始有了活力
the market for art and literature has been bustling recently.
We'll soon be earning
我们也在东站附近租一个地方
nearly as much as porters at the Gare de L'Est.
It's true.
没错
Works of art are selling like pancakes.
卖艺术品是好主意
Then it's agreed.
就因为如此
Tomorrow we take the girls shopping to indulge their feminine whims.
明天带女朋友去购物
Sunday we'll go on a picnic in the countryside.
星期天到乡下玩
What about me?
我呢
You have two days to find yourself a companion.
到周日之前弄一个恋人出来
It's not our fault if your appearance sparks no interest in the opposite sex.
你连喜欢的女人都没找到
But if you have no luck, you can still come along...
没找到也要来你当司机
as our driver.
Monsieur, there's a call for you in the kitchen.
有电话找你
Madame... your eyes are like two moons.
夫人  你的眼镜就像月亮一样美丽
Let's hope it doesn't come to more than 600 francs.
都是廉价商品也好
波特里
And never come back!
扔掉吧
They didn't like it?
不行吗
Idiots!
像傻瓜一样
They tried to discourage me.
没有长眼睛
They said I should break my brushes in two
但我不会折断笔  然后再自杀
and jump out the window.
Let's go borrow some money from Marcel
跟马歇尔借点钱吃点什么吧
and go out to eat.
I gave you
我给你们钱
a cash advance.
I want it back
两天之内一定要还给我
in two days. Not three or five.
只有两天
Two days. Good luck...
已经结束了
and good-bye.
再见
一群白痴
What was that all about?
为什么关门了
He's mad that I serialized my play.
我的连载不合他们的脾胃
Says it didn't suit the magazine's style and that readers complained.
他们完全不考虑读者的心情
What readers? Besides, as editor in chief, I set the style.
决定编辑方针的是我
He was just the publisher. Capitalist!
那个资本主义家伙
- I'm hungry. - Me too.
肚子饿了 我也是
Come eat at my place.
在家里吃吧
I happen to have a little money.
我有东西吃
While we're at it, I can play my latest composition for you.
顺便可以给你们听我的新曲
你被逮捕了
I'm going to leave Marcel.
我要离开马歇尔
When?
什么时候
Tonight.
今天晚上
I've already packed.
我已经收拾好了
Does he know?
他怎么说
I didn't dare tell him.
不知道
I'm going back to Strasbourg. There's this farmer there.
回到故乡和富翁结婚
He's not great-looking, but he's sweet...
就算长得不帅  只要慈祥又真心就可以了
and dependable.
Why?
那马歇尔怎么办
Marcel doesn't need me.
不需要我
All he loves is his books.
对他来说书就是全部
Yesterday I pawned my ring for rent money.
我为了房租连戒指都当进去了
I left the money on the table. When I came back, he'd taken it...
他就用那个钱全都买书看
and spent it all on first-edition Balzacs.
而且买的是巴尔扎克的书
Poor Marcel.
可怜的男人
He'll forget me in a week.
别忘了我
In any case, quicker than I'll forget him.
不知不觉间
That's how men are.
男人都是薄情的
Will you see me to the station? - Of course.
送我去车站吧
I'll miss you.
当然我会很寂寞的
You must come visit!
来见我
I'll send you the fare.
我会给你车费如果是富翁  那肯定很有钱
The man's rich. I promise.
我一定去
Write to me care of general delivery.
要给我写信
Why general delivery?
你要分手吗
I don't know.
不知道
开往斯特拉斯夫的列车
马上就要发车了  乘客请上车
How's it going, Mimi?
你还好吗
Fine.
是的
Can I give you a ride?
坐上来吧
You can drive me home.
送我回家吧
Yes, darling.
洛特勒夫 你想怎么样
I found work.
我要工作
You needn't have.
没必要工作
I can't go on living like this, never having any money.
我无法忍受贫穷的生活
I can't breathe. It's like I'm suffocating.
我快无法呼吸了
I'll open the window.
要我开窗户吗
That won't help. Besides, it's already cold in here.
傻瓜是为了家计才这样
Shall I light a fire in the stove?
我给你开暖炉吧
There's no wood or coal.
没有燃料
Some old poems of mine.
这是我的诗
I thought I'd publish a collection...
我一直想出自己的诗集
someday.
At least they'll provide some heat.
你会多少感到温暖
I'm going for a little walk.
我去散散心
Don't be too long.
早点回来
Hello, Rodolfo.
洛特勒夫
Hello, Mimi.
眯米
I love you, you know, but life is hard.
虽然我爱你  但无法忍受贫穷的生活
Yes. I understand.
我很清楚
I drink.
Glass after glass
To forget all about my wife's friends
I drink.
Glass after glass
To forget all my troubles
I drink.
Any old swill
As long as it's strong
I drink.
The cheapest stuff
It's rough
But it passes the time
Is life really such a lark?
Is it really so exciting?
I ask
Those two questions AUTUMN
秋天
Is it worth living?
Or loving, only to be cheated on?
I ask those two questions
But no one ever answers
And so I drink
Glass after glass
What?
怎么样
Nothing.
没什么
It's very good.
真不错
The voice of the people is the voice of God.
人声就是天籁
EVEN MOSES USED BLANCHERON SUGAR
佛朗修罗砂糖公司
That there is known as turkey with truffles.
你们看
火鸟料理已经结束了
Look at the color of that leg of lamb!
还有烤得热烘烘的羊羔
Lamb is the favorite food of the gods
是桑德拉夫人非常喜欢的东西
and also of my godmother, Madame Chandlier.
And what about those trout? They're superb swimmers.
还有这个鳟鱼  这家伙可是游泳名将
They climb rapids as quickly
如果有人请我们去吃晚餐  我们会比它更快
as we'd accept an invitation to dinner this evening.
That fruit is known as pineapple.
还有菠萝
I almost got to taste one once.
我吃过一次
Speaking of fruit,
果实也可以但也不想失去肉
I wouldn't say no to that pheasant there. Why this profusion of delicacies?
为什么会走这么快
You don't know? It's All Saints' Day,
不知道吗
a great family celebration.
今天是家人  都团聚在一起的圣诞节
Would you care to spend the evening with me?
我们也庆祝吧
No money.
没有钱
How much have you got?
有多少
I don't understand. I've lost my appetite.
我没有食欲
Same here.
我也是
I can see
我可以看到
that a phantom from the past sits at this table.
过去的亡灵正坐在台上
But if you intend to waste away to nothing,
如果有勇气饿死
you could do so just as well on a full stomach.
也可以吃饱撑死
Am I disturbing you?
妨碍你们了吗
Come in.
进来吧
I'm so cold.
真冷啊
I happened to be passing by
走在路上
and saw the light in the window.
可以看到窗户里的灯光
I lost my apartment a week ago,
上周我被赶出来
and I've been wandering the streets ever since.
在街上流浪了
I'm posing for artists these days,
也当过模特  但也赚不到多少钱
but it doesn't pay much.
Oh, I only show my face and hands.
只是手和脸的模特
They've promised to pay me tomorrow.
明天我可以拿到钱
Then I'll move back into my apartment.
我想回到家里
- Where are you two going? - To get some cigars.
去哪里 去买雪茄
In Havana.
一直到巴西
We'll be back tomorrow
我们明天早上会回来
sure as arrows loosed by a steady hand.
Where have you been?
你一直呆在哪里了
Don't ask any questions.
什么也别问了
Just let me sit here by your side.
我想留在你身边  这里是温暖的
It's so warm here.
I'll stay until tomorrow. All right?
我能和你在一起吗
It's going to be very cold here.
这里很冷
Good.
好吧
It'll be just like before.
真像以前一样
I'll clear the table.
我来收拾吧
The warmth has made me dizzy. I can hardly stand up.
因为热所以头都晕了  站不起来
You have a fever.
你发烧
I'll help you into bed.
我带你到床上躺下
Schaunard and I will go get a doctor.
我和肖纳罗去叫医生
You stay here and keep Mimi company.
帮我照顾眯米
I was awake the whole time.
他一直都没睡觉
Rodolfo still loves me.
他还爱着我
What about you?
你呢
I never stopped loving him.
我也爱他
Then all is well.
太好了
I'm going away forever.
但我要去远行
What are you talking about?
什么意思
I'm going to die soon.
我马上会死
Look.
你看
You believe me now?
知道了吧
If I'd stayed here
如果和洛特勒夫安宁的生活
with Rodolfo,
everything would be fine now.
这种事情就不会...
Poor Rodolfo.
真是可怜的人
He has to take care of me once again.
我还对他迷恋
But not for long.
这也结束了
The last dress he buys me will be white.
最后我想穿白色的衣服
Don't talk like that. You'll get better. Rodolfo has gone for a doctor.
不你马上就能好奇来  医生会治好你
It took me an hour to climb the stairs yesterday.
上楼梯也要用尽全力
But if I'd found another woman here with him,
如果这里有别的女人
I'd have thrown myself right out the window.
我会从窗户跳下去
Rodolfo knows everything.
他会知道
She must go to the hospital - my hospital.
如果现在再马上住院不行
I'll call an ambulance.
叫急救车吧
I have a car.
我们有车
You must be brave.
你要坚强的面对
I can ease her pain, but I can't save her.
很遗憾但已经晚了
She'll live until spring at the latest.
就算最长  也只能维持到春天
I can keep her in a private room, but I must warn you:
会在特别护理室悉心照顾
Though it may seem cruel, it's very expensive.
虽然很难启齿  但住院费很贵
I'll find the money.
我会弄到钱
Who painted this? Becker?
这是贝卡的画吗
Open the curtains.
献给约尔玛·卡里斯玛基 请拉开窗帘
Spring is here, and I want to look outside.
我想看到春天的景色
It's so grey in here.
这里太阴了
Why don't you pick me some flowers?
帮我摘一朵花给我
She's dead.
死了
Shall we come with you?
我们一起走
That's all right.
不我想一个人
I need to be alone.